Damon Knight Papers
Damon Knight Papers
1956-1978
Knight, Damon,1922-2002.
10.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, science fiction short story writer and novelist. Typescript manuscript stories and novels, galley proofs, and Knight's subject files which include clippings, correspondence, photographs, and printed material about authors, publishers, organizations, and miscellaneous subjects.
149109
Biographical History
Damon Francis Knight (1922–2002) was an award-winning American science fiction author, editor, and critic. His first story was published in 1941 in the science fiction pulp magazine Amazing Stories; over his career he has written novels, short stories, criticism and other non-fiction, and edited numerous anthologies. His best-known short story is "To Serve Man," which was adapted into a Twilight Zone episode.
Knight was a founding member of the Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers of America (SFWA), cofounder of the National Fantasy Fan Federation, cofounder of the Milford Writer's Workshop, and -- with his wife, author Kate Wilhelm -- cofounder of the Clarion Writers Workshop. These two highly-regarded writers' workshops have produced a remarkable number of award-winning writers, including Octavia Butler, Cory Doctorow, Vonda McIntyre, Kim Stanley Robinson, and Bruce Sterling.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Damon Knight Collection consists of general files, writings, writings by other authors, and miscellaneous. There is also a set of later additions which has not yet been integrated into the main collection.
General files contains folders on a wide range of individuals, topics, organizations, and ideas. There is also biographical information about Knight.
Writings is broken down into two categories, published material and unpublished material. Published material is made up of known anthologies, novels, short stories, and critical essays. The folders include rough drafts, typescripts, correspondence, reviews, royalty receipts, etc. for each title. Unpublished material, for the most part, is composed of short stories. Also to be found in this series are joint undertakings, unfinished material, an outline, and a project.
Writings by other authors contains translations from the French of various authors, and writings in English by American and other authors. Authors include Rene Barjavel, James Bliss, Ursula K. LeGuin, R. A. Lafferty, Joanna Russ and more.
Miscellaneous material consists of miscellaneous unidentifiable pages of various writings and jacket covers, fragments, tape recordings, cartoons (by Knight), index cards relating to Fortean research on psychic phenomena, an untitled galley, and handwritten notes of unknown origin.
1980 additions contains later additions that have not been integrated into the previous accessions -- primarily writings but also some correspondence and printed material as well as material related to The Futurians, an organization of which Knight was a member. Much of the writings relates to the Orbit anthologies (Orbit 12 through Orbit 17).
Arrangement of the Collection
General files are arranged alphabetically. Writings is subdivided into published and unpublished; within that items are arranged alphabetically by type and then by title. Writings by other authors is subdivided into two categories: translations from the French, and English writers. Both sections are arranged alphabetically according to the author's last name.
Related Material
has a number of collections relating to science fiction and fantasy authors and publications, both in the manuscript collections and in our Rare Books collection. See the for a listing of manuscript collections, and refer to for a listing of cataloged books and publications.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Science fiction; Knight, Damon, 1922-2002 -- Archives.; American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Science fiction, American.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notes (documents); Photographs.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- General files
  - Ackerman (Box 1)
  - Addressograph (Box 1)
  - Advent Publishers (Box 1)
  - Altshuler (Box 1)
  - American-English Dictionary (Box 1)
  - Argot (Box 1)
  - Arrivals and Departures (Box 1)
  - Artists (Box 1)
  - Astronomical (Box 1)
  - Assassins (Box 1)
  - Austin, William N. (Box 1)
  - Beaumont, Charles (Box 1)
  - Berkley Novels
    - Davidson (Box 1)
    - Dickson (Box 1)
    - Disch (Box 1)
    - Farmer (Box 1)
    - Harrison (Box 1)
    - Hayes (Box 1)
    - Herbert (Box 1)
    - Jesby (Box 1)
    - Laumer, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Nelson (Box 1)
    - Thomas/Wilhelm (Box 1)
    - Wilhelm (Box 1)
    - Zelazny (Box 1)
  - Bills, Receipts (Box 1)
  - Bio (Box 1)
  - Biographical Data (Box 1)
  - Blackbeard, Wm. (Box 1)
  - Bluenoses and Philistines (Box 1)
  - Boggs (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews (Box 1)
  - Books (Box 1)
  - Books, Publishing History (Box 1)
  - Bookshelf of America (Box 1)
  - Book-Of-The-Month Club (Box 1)
  - Book Purchases, 1961; 1962; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Boucher (Box 1)
  - Boyer, Nick (Box 1)
  - Bradbury (Box 1)
  - Britannica Reports (Box 1)
  - Budrys, Algis, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cabin Boy (Box 1)
  - Campbell, John W. Jr. (Box 1)
  - Caper (Box 1)
  - Ceiling (Box 1)
  - Charts, Tables, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cheever (Box 1)
  - Chess (Box 1)
  - Chess Code (Box 1)
  - Chessmen Designs (Box 1)
  - Christmas Cards (Box 1)
  - Ciardi (Box 1)
  - Clara (Box 1)
  - Arthur C. Clarke (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Coffee (Box 1)
  - College Applications (Box 1)
  - Coleman, Sid (Box 1)
  - Communications (Box 1)
  - Communism (Box 1)
  - Computer Stories (Box 1)
  - Computers (Box 1)
  - Conklin (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cosmology (Box 1)
  - Courthouse (Box 1)
  - Crackpots (Box 1)
  - Crime (Box 1)
  - Critical History of Science Fiction S-F (Notes) (Box 1)
  - Criticism (Box 1)
  - Crossen (Box 1)
  - Crosswords (Box 1)
  - Cults (Box 1)
  - Davenport, Basil (Box 1)
  - Deane, Davidson (Box 1)
  - De Camp (Box 1)
  - Del Rey, Lester (Box 1)
  - Del Rey-Harrison (Box 1)
  - Delaware Valley Telephone Co. (Box 1)
  - Dick, Philip K. (Box 1)
  - Dickson (Box 1)
  - Doorway Novel (Box 1)
  - Economists (Box 1)
  - Education (Box 1)
  - Electronics (Box 1)
  - Ellison, Harlan (Box 1)
  - Embarassing moments (Box 1)
  - Emshwiller, Ed and Carol (Box 1)
  - Engineering (Box 1)
  - Epigraphs (Box 1)
  - Eripmav (Box 2)
  - Eskimos (Box 2)
  - Esperanto (Box 2)
  - Fan correspondence (Box 2)
  - Fan letters, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Fans (Box 2)
  - Fickas (Box 2)
  - Fiction and Science Fiction (F and SF) Book Co. (Witter) (Box 2)
  - Fine and Ward (Box 2)
  - Fortean Society (Box 2)
  - Foundation for the Study of Cycles (Box 2)
  - Friend, Oscar (Box 2)
  - Freaks (Box 2)
  - Freeloaders (Box 2)
  - Fultz (Box 2)
  - Games (Box 2)
  - General Artist Corporation (Box 2)
  - German science fiction stories and correspondence (Box 2)
  - Gold (Box 2)
  - Greenberg (Box 2)
  - Grennell (Box 2)
  - Harness (Box 2)
  - Harrison (Box 2)
  - Helen (Box 2)
  - Holt, Rinehart and Winston (Box 2)
  - The Hugo Losers (Box 2)
  - Ideas (Box 2)
  - IF-Correspondence (Box 2)
  - INFO (Box 2)
  - Insurance (Box 2)
  - International Fantasy Awards (Box 2)
  - Janifer, Lawrence M. (Box 2)
  - Jews (Box 2)
  - Johnson, W. Ryerson (Box 2)
  - Journal (Box 2)
  - Journalists (Box 2)
  - Kinsey (Box 2)
  - Kornbluth (Box 2)
  - Laumer, Keith (Box 2)
  - Laura and Chet (Box 2)
  - Letters (Box 2)
  - Levinson (Box 2)
  - Library of Science (Box 2)
  - Linard (Box 2)
  - Literary characters (Box 2)
  - London (Box 2)
  - Lowndes (Box 2)
  - Lunar Colony (Box 2)
  - McCain, Vernon L. (Box 2)
  - McCarthy (Box 2)
  - McCary, Bob (Box 2)
  - Magazine lists (Box 2)
  - Mail order lists (Box 2)
  - Malaya (Box 2)
  - Mankind Fashions (Hong Kong) (Box 2)
  - Maps (Box 2)
  - Mary (Box 2)
  - The Meadows of Steel (anthology) (Box 2)
  - Medicine (Box 2)
  - Metallurgy (Box 2)
  - Methods (Box 2)
  - Mexico (Box 2)
  - Mid-Century Book Society (Box 2)
  - Mom (Box 2)
  - Monopolies (Box 2)
  - Museum Directors (Box 2)
  - Mystery Writers of America, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Natural History (Box 2)
  - National Translation Center (Box 2)
  - Nebula (Box 2)
  - Negroes (Box 2)
  - Night of Light (Box 2)
  - Notebooks (Box 2)
  - Notes (Box 2)
  - Notes-Forts (Box 2)
  - Nuclear physics (Box 2)
  - Nuclear power plants (Box 2)
  - Nuclear weapons (Box 2)
  - Nuetzel, Charles (Box 2)
  - Nutrition (Box 2)
  - Personal, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Painters (Box 3)
  - Perverts (Box 3)
  - Philologists, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Philosophers (Box 3)
  - Photos (Box 3)
  - Physicists (Box 3)
  - Physics (Box 3)
  - Pictorial (Box 3)
  - Poems (Box 3)
  - Poets (Box 3)
  - Polite (Box 3)
  - Political Philosophy (Box 3)
  - Politicians (Box 3)
  - Planete (Box 3)
  - Predictions (Box 3)
  - Primitive art (Box 3)
  - Professional expenses (Box 3)
  - Professional Printing Co., Inc. (Box 3)
  - Proof Incorporated (Box 3)
  - Prospectuses (Box 3)
  - Prosthetics (Box 3)
  - Pseudoscience (Box 3)
  - Psychology data (Box 3)
  - Psychiatry (Box 3)
  - Publishing (Box 3)
  - Quotations (Box 3)
  - Radio-television (Box 3)
  - Recipes (Box 3)
  - Regress (Box 3)
  - Revisions (Box 3)
  - Reynolds (Box 3)
  - Richmonds (Box 3)
  - Rome (Box 3)
  - Royalty (Box 3)
  - Saints (Box 3)
  - Sawyers, Inc. (View Master) (Box 3)
  - Science fiction
    - Adventures (Box 3)
    - Forum, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Sculptors (Box 3)
  - Security (Box 3)
  - Shaw, Larry (Box 3)
  - Shaw, Bob (Box 3)
  - Sidgwick and Jackson, Ltd. (Box 3)
  - Singers (Box 3)
  - Smith, Evelyn E. (Box 3)
  - Space travel (Box 3)
  - Spain (Box 3)
  - Square pegs (Box 3)
  - Super checkers (Box 3)
  - Switzerland (Box 3)
  - Synthetics (Box 3)
  - Television (Box 3)
  - Television ideas (Box 3)
  - Testimony (Box 3)
  - Time finance (Box 3)
  - To Be Continued (Box 3)
  - Transvestites (Box 3)
  - Trixie (Box 3)
  - Trudy (Box 3)
  - Tucker, Bob (Box 3)
  - Turkey (Box 3)
  - UFO's (Unidentified Flying Objects) (Box 3)
  - Uncivilization (Box 3)
  - Universities (Box 3)
  - Valerie (Box 3)
  - Velikovsky (Box 3)
  - Warner, Sylvia Townsend (Box 3)
  - White, E.B. (Box 3)
  - White, James (Box 3)
  - Willis (Box 3)
  - Witchcraft (Box 3)
  - Writers (Box 3)
  - Xerox copies of articles (Box 3)
  - Zoology (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Published material
    - Reviews, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Anthologies
      - A Century of Great Short Science Fiction Novels, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - A Century of Science Fiction, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Orbit 3, typescript (Box 4)
      - Orbit 4, typescript (Box 4)
      - Cities of Wonder, typescript, galley proofs (Box 4)
    - Novels
      - A For Anything, galley, partial; 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Charles Fort, Prophet of the Unexplained
        - Notes (Box 4)
        - Typescript (Box 4)
        - Galleys, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Hell's Pavement, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Masks (Box 5)
      - Mind Switch, galley (Box 5)
      - The Rithian Terror (Box 5)
      - Three Novels, typescript (Box 5)
      - Rule Golden, typescript, galleys, book; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - World Without Children, typescript, galley; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Worlds to Come, typescripts, galley; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Short stories
      - Don't Live In the Past (Box 6)
      - Far Out (Box 6)
      - Natural State (Box 6)
      - Turning On, typescript, galley; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Critical essays
      - In Search of Wonder, 1956; 1960,; 1967; 3 volumes (Box 6)
  - Unpublished material
    - Articles
      - Oddities From Heaven (Box 6)
      - The Next Ten Years in Science Fiction (Box 6)
    - Short stories
      - The Affair of the Upside Down House (Box 6)
      - A Likely Story (Box 6)
      - Anachron (Box 6)
      - The Analogues (Box 6)
      - Another World (Box 6)
      - Are You Tied On (Box 6)
      - Ask Me Anything (Box 6)
      - Auto Da-fe (Box 6)
      - The Avenger (Box 6)
      - Babel II (Box 6)
      - Back to Death, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - The Banjo of Bildad O'Shane (Box 7)
      - Be My Guest (Box 7)
      - Beachcomber (Box 7)
      - The Big Pat Boom (Box 7)
      - Blackout (Box 7)
      - The Blind Pilot (Box 7)
      - The Blue Papa (Box 7)
      - The Blue Rose (Box 7)
      - The Bullet From Nowhere (Box 7)
      - Cabin Boy (Box 7)
      - Catch That Martian (Box 7)
      - The Coach (Box 7)
      - Collectors Item (Box 7)
      - The Cornered Rabbit (Box 7)
      - Corpus Delicti (Box 7)
      - The Country of the Kind (Box 7)
      - The Cube (Box 7)
      - Days of Darkness (Box 7)
      - Death With Father (Box 7)
      - Decline and Fall (Box 7)
      - Definition (Box 7)
      - The Devil's God-Daughter (Box 7)
      - D 10 (Box 7)
      - Double Meaning (Box 7)
      - Down Went Polly (Box 7)
      - Dulcie and Decorum (Box 7)
      - The Earthquarter, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - The Enemy (Box 7)
      - Eros (Box 7)
      - Extempore (Box 7)
      - An Eye for a What (Box 7)
      - Eairy Tales (Box 7)
      - Faun's Lament (Box 7)
      - Finnegan's Wake (Box 7)
      - The First Days of May (Box 7)
      - The Fog (Box 7)
      - Four In One (Box 7)
      - The Flower of Venus (Box 7)
      - Freudian Slip (Box 7)
      - From Where I Sit (Box 7)
      - Fritch Video Crap (Box 7)
      - Giant Killer (Box 7)
      - God's Nose (Box 7)
      - Gook-Harpies Bazoo (Box 7)
      - The Handler (Box 7)
      - Homecoming (Box 7)
      - Identity (Box 7)
      - Idiot Stick (Box 7)
      - If Thy Right Eye Offend Thee (Box 7)
      - In Defense of Bad English (Box 7)
      - In Defense of Beards (Box 7)
      - In The Beginning (Box 7)
      - The Identical Men (Box 7)
      - The Indigestible Invaders (Box 7)
      - The Innocence of Evil (Box 7)
      - Insurance (Box 7)
      - It's Sport Or Is It (Box 7)
      - The Last Word (Box 7)
      - The Leg in the Wood Lot (Box 7)
      - Legacy (Box 8)
      - Leveque's Wife (Box 8)
      - Logogenetics (Box 8)
      - Lords of The Earth (Box 8)
      - Maid to Measure (Box 8)
      - Man In the Jar (Box 8)
      - The Man Who Played Satan (Box 8)
      - The Mangel (Box 8)
      - The Mighty Fallen (Box 8)
      - Murder's Weekend (Box 8)
      - No World for One (Box 8)
      - Not With A Bang (Box 8)
      - Pigskin Phoenix (Box 8)
      - The Prodigal Corpse (Box 8)
      - The Quarrel (Box 8)
      - The Rat (Box 8)
      - The Second Class Citizen (Box 8)
      - Semper Fi (Box 8)
      - Shoot And Be Damned (Box 8)
      - The Small Snatch (Box 8)
      - The Solar Comedy (Box 8)
      - Soundings (Box 8)
      - Special Delivery (Box 8)
      - Stranger Station (Box 8)
      - Strictly Fantastic (Box 8)
      - Surface Tension (Box 8)
      - Thing of Beauty (Box 8)
      - The Third Little Green Man (Box 8)
      - Ticket to Nowhere (Box 8)
      - Time Enough (Box 8)
      - The Tokens (Box 8)
      - They're Not Going Anywhere -- But Let's Say Goodbye (Box 8)
      - To Be Continued (Box 8)
      - To Serve Man (Box 8)
      - Too Big For Boothill (Box 8)
      - Too Many Crooks (Box 8)
      - The Tree of Time (Box 8)
      - Truly Human (Box 8)
      - Turncoat (Box 8)
      - Undead on Arrival (Box 8)
      - What Rough Beast, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - What You Don't Know (Box 8)
      - Who? What? Where? When? Why? (Box 8)
      - Why Don't You Die? (Box 8)
      - We Live Inside (Box 8)
      - The World On The Border (Box 8)
      - The Worshippers (Box 8)
      - Year One, Age of Space (Box 8)
      - You're Another (Box 8)
  - Joint Undertakings
    - Short stories
      - Peephole (Box 8)
      - Mate In Four (Box 8)
      - The Enigma of V 51 (Box 8)
    - Unfinished material
      - Four In One (Box 8)
    - Outline for juvenile science fiction novels (Box 8)
    - Pulpwood Anthology Project (Box 8)
- Writings by other authors
  - Translated from French
    - Barjavel, Rene
      - Ashes, Ashes
        - Rough Draft (Box 8)
        - Typescript; galleys, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - The Time Drivers (Box 9)
      - Le Voyageur Imprudent (Box 9)
    - Berthorrel, Pierre
      - Si Les Femmes Metaient Comptees (Box 9)
    - Cheinisse, Claude F.
      - The Dead Fish (Box 9)
      - Juliette (Box 9)
      - Contes Pour Les Enfants Pas Sages (Box 9)
      - A Sense of History (Box 9)
      - The Suicide (Box 9)
    - Damonti
      - Olivia (Box 9)
      - The Non-Humans (Box 9)
      - The Notary and The Conspiracy (Box 9)
    - Henneberg
      - The Gods Are Born (Box 9)
      - The Rose of the Country of Roses (Box 9)
    - Hougron
      - Monster World (Box 9)
    - Le Fevre
      - Hot and Cold (Box 9)
  - English writers
    - Anderson, Poul
      - The Disinherited (Box 9)
    - Blish, James
      - An Expectation (Box 9)
      - Maeterlinck (Box 9)
      - Theory of Right Action (Box 9)
      - The Coming Forth (Box 9)
      - Tabby, Dead (Box 9)
      - Atalantidon (Box 9)
    - Borman, Sonya
      - Splice of Life (Box 9)
    - Conway, Ritter
      - A Baker's Dozen for Boothill (Box 9)
    - Cox, Arthur Jean
      - Fame (Box 9)
    - Disch, Thomas B.
      - The Asian Shore (Box 9)
    - Fleming, Stuart
      - Doorway to Kel-jar (Box 9)
      - New Day on Aurora (Box 9)
      - The Secret of Kaljmar (Box 9)
    - Forbes, Charles
      - Message Found on a Microscope (Box 9)
    - Kidd, Virginia
      - Kangaroo Court (Box 9)
    - Lafferty, R.A.
      - Entire and Perfect Chrysolite (Box 10)
      - The Hole On The Corner (Box 9)
    - LeGuin, Ursula
      - The End (Box 9)
    - McKenna, Richard
      - The Secret Place (Box 9)
    - Rice, Allison
      - The Loolies are here (Box 10)
    - Russ, Joanna
      - Second inquisition (Box 10)
    - Scott, Robin
      - Maybe Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, Chevalier de Lamarck, was a little bit right (Box 10)
    - Sererence, Felix
      - Aillinn o' my dreams (Box 10)
    - Thorp, Roderick
      - Sunburst (Box 10)
    - Wilhelm, Kate
      - A cold dark night with snow (Box 10)
    - Wolfe, Gene
      - How the whip came back (Box 10)
      - Eyebem (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Fragments (Box 10)
  - Cartoons (Box 10)
  - Holograph notes (Box 10)
  - Galley, untitled (Box 11)
  - Fortean research file (10" 3x5 cards) (Box 11)
  - Tape recordings, reel-to-reel, 5 reels (Box 11)
- 1980 accession
  - Orbit 12
    - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Typescript (Box 12)
    - Typescript (fragments) (Box 12)
  - Orbit 13
    - Correspondence, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Galley - author proof (Box 12)
  - Orbit 14
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Typescript (fragments) (Box 12)
    - Galley - readers proof (Box 12)
    - Page proofs (Box 13)
  - Orbit 15
    - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Page proofs - master set - 1st pass (Box 13)
    - Page proofs - master set - 3rd pass (Box 13)
  - Orbit 16
    - Shot copy (Box 13)
    - Page proofs, master set, 1st pass (Box 13)
    - Page proofs,master set, 3rd pass (Box 13)
  - Orbit 17
    - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Page proofs, master set, 1st pass (incomplete) (Box 13)
    - Page proofs, master set, 3rd pass (Box 13)
  - Futurians
    - Correspondence (Box 13)
    - Interviews (Box 13)
    - Research material, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Research material? Michel, John, "Best laugh in the world", tsc. (Box 13)
    - Illustrative material (Box 13)
    - Photographs (Box 13)
    - Negatives (Box 14)
    - Typescript, corrected, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Typescript, photocopy, corrected, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - working draft, misc. pages, 8 folders (Box 14)
    - Galley - master set corrected (Box 14)
    - Galley - index and material for index, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Futurian Science Literary Society
    - Minutes of meeting, 1938 (Box 15)
    - Financial records, 1938 (Box 15)
  - Golden road
    - Correspondence, 1 item (Box 15)
    - Manuscript, photocopied printed material; 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Science fiction of the thirties
    - Manuscript, photocopied printed material; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Westerns of the forties
    - Manuscript, photocopied printed material; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1972; 1978; 2 items (Box 16)
  - "The Starlost" / Ellison, Harlan, photocopies printed material (Box 16)